(Applause)
(تصفيق)
AIDS was discovered 1981; the virus, 1983.
أكتشف مرض نقص المناعة المكتسبة "الإيدز" عام 1981، والفيروس عام 1983
These Gapminder bubbles show you
فقاعات الـ"غاب مايندر" تظهر لكم
how the spread of the virus was in 1983 in the world,
كيفية إنتشار الفيروس في العالم عام 1983
or how we estimate that it was.
أو كما قدرنا إنتشاره
What we are showing here is --
وما نقوم بعرضه هنا
on this axis here, I'm showing percent of infected adults.
على هذا المحور هنا، نسبة المصابين من البالغين
And on this axis, I'm showing dollars per person in income.
وعلى هذا المحور، الدخل بالدولار للشخص الواحد
And the size of these bubbles, the size of the bubbles here,
وحجم الفقاعات، الفقاعات الموجودة هنا
that shows how many are infected in each country,
تعكس عدد المصابين في كل دولة
and the color is the continent.
واللون هنا يمثل القارة
Now, you can see United States, in 1983,
الآن يمكنكم ملاحظة الولايات التحدة في عام 1983
had a very low percentage infected,
كانت فيها نسبة قليلة جداً مصابة
but due to the big population, still a sizable bubble.
لكن لكبر عدد السكان، فإن الفقاعة كبيرة نسبياً
There were quite many people infected in the United States.
كثير من الناس كانوا مصابين في الولايات المتحدة
And, up there, you see Uganda.
وفي الأعلى هناك، ترون أوغندا
They had almost five percent infected,
وصلت نسبة المصابين فيها إلى خمسة بالمائة تقريباً
and quite a big bubble in spite of being a small country, then.
وتمثلها فقاعة كبيرة على الرغم من كونها دولة صغيرة
And they were probably the most infected country in the world.
وكانت الدولة التي تحوي أكبر عدد من المصابين في العالم آنذاك
Now, what has happened?
والآن ماذا حدث؟
Now you have understood the graph
الآن وقد فهمتم هذا المخطط البياني
and now, in the next 60 seconds,
والآن، خلال الستين ثانية الآتية
we will play the HIV epidemic in the world.
سنعرض إنتشار فيروس نقص المناعة في العالم
But first, I have a new invention here.
ولكن قبل ذلك، لدي اختراع جديد هنا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I have solidified the beam of the laser pointer.
لقد قمت بتصليب شعاع مؤشر الليزر
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So, ready, steady, go!
إذن، استعد، جاهز، إنطلق!
First, we have the fast rise in Uganda and Zimbabwe.
أولاً لدينا ارتفاع سريع في أوغندا وزيمبابوي
They went upwards like this.
ارتفعوا هكذا
In Asia, the first country to be heavily infected was Thailand --
وفي آسيا، أول دولة انتشرت بها الإصابة بحدة كانت تايلاند
they reached one to two percent.
وصلوا إلى ما بين واحد واثنان في المائة
Then, Uganda started to turn back,
بعد ذلك أوغندا بدأت بالتراجع
whereas Zimbabwe skyrocketed,
في حين زيمبابوي وصلت علو السماء
and some years later South Africa had a terrible rise of HIV frequency.
وبعد عدة سنوات، ارتفعت نسبة الإصابة بالفيروس في جنوب أفريقيا بشدة
Look, India got many infected,
انظروا، أصيب العديد في الهند
but had a low level.
ولكن على مستوى ضعيف
And almost the same happens here.
والشيء ذاته تقريباً يتكررهنا
See, Uganda coming down, Zimbabwe coming down,
انظروا، أوغندا تنخفض، وزيمبابوي تنخفض
Russia went to one percent.
روسيا وصلت إلى واحد في المائة
In the last two to three years,
في آخر سنتين أو ثلاث
we have reached a steady state of HIV epidemic in the world.
وصلنا لمستوى ثابت من وباء نقص المناعة المكتسبة في العالم
25 years it took.
قد تطلب ذلك 25 سنة
But, steady state doesn't mean that things are getting better,
ولكن هذا التوازن لايعني أن الأمور تتحسن
it's just that they have stopped getting worse.
بل مجرد أنها توقفت من الإتجاه للأسوأ
And it has -- the steady state is, more or less,
والحال الآن أن ما يقارب واحد في المائة
one percent of the adult world population is HIV-infected.
من عدد سكان العالم البالغين مصابون بنقص المناعة المكتسبة
It means 30 to 40 million people,
أي ما يعادل بين 30 و 40 مليون شخصاً
the whole of California -- every person,
كما لو أن كل شخص في كاليفورنيا مصاب
that's more or less what we have today in the world.
هذه هي حالة العالم اليوم تقريباً
Now, let me make a fast replay of Botswana.
الآن اسمحوا لي أن أقوم بإعادة عرض بوتسوانا سريعاً
Botswana -- upper middle-income country in southern Africa,
بوتسوانا -- دولة في جنوب أفريقيا ذات دخل متوسط إلى علوي
democratic government, good economy,
فيها حكومة ديمقراطية واقتصاد جيد
and this is what happened there.
وهذا ما حدث هناك
They started low, they skyrocketed,
بدأوا بدرجة منخفضة ثم ارتفعوا بسرعة
they peaked up there in 2003,
وصلوا إلى أعلى درجة هناك عام 2003
and now they are down.
والآن تراجعوا
But they are falling only slowly,
ولكنهم يتدرجون ببطء
because in Botswana, with good economy and governance,
والسبب أنه بوجود اقتصاد وحكم جيدان في بوتسوانا
they can manage to treat people.
يمكن توفير العلاج للناس
And if people who are infected are treated, they don't die of AIDS.
وإذا ما تم علاج المصابين بالفيروس، فلن يموتوا بسبب الإيدز
These percentages won't come down
وهذه النسب لن تنخفض
because people can survive 10 to 20 years.
لأن الناس، رغم مرضهم، يمكنهم العيش من 10 إلى 20 سنة
So there's some problem with these metrics now.
هناك بعض المشاكل في المقاييس الآن
But the poorer countries in Africa, the low-income countries down here,
لكن الدول الأكثر فقراً في أفريقيا، الدول ذات الدخل المنخفض في الأسفل هنا
there the rates fall faster, of the percentage infected,
نسبة المصابين هناك تنخفض بسرعة أكبر
because people still die.
لأن الناس يموتون باستمرار
In spite of PEPFAR, the generous PEPFAR,
على الرغم من خطة رئيس الولايات المتحدة الطارئة للإغاثة من الإيدز PEPFAR
all people are not reached by treatment,
تلك الخطة الكريمة، فإن العلاج لا يصل جميع الناس
and of those who are reached by treatment in the poor countries,
وبين الذين يصلهم العلاج في الدول الفقيرة
only 60 percent are left on treatment after two years.
ستون بالمائة فقط يتابعون العلاج بعد سنيتين
It's not realistic with lifelong treatment
هذا ليس واقعي لتوفير علاج يستمر مدى الحياة
for everyone in the poorest countries.
لجميع الناس في أفقر الدول
But it's very good that what is done is being done.
لكنه من الجيد جداً أن كل ما تم القيام به بالفعل حاصل
But focus now is back on prevention.
لكن التركيزالآن يعود إلى الوقاية
It is only by stopping the transmission
فلن يتمكن العالم من التحكم بالمرض
that the world will be able to deal with it.
حتى يقوموا بإيقاف إنتشار العدوى
Drugs is too costly -- had we had the vaccine,
العقاقير باهظة جداً -- لو وجد لقاح
or when we will get the vaccine, that's something more effective --
أو بالأحرى عند توفر اللقاح، يكون ذلك أمراً أكثر فعالية
but the drugs are very costly for the poor.
ولكن العقاقير مكلفة جداً للفقراء
Not the drug in itself, but the treatment
ليس العقار نفسه وإنما هو العلاج
and the care which is needed around it.
والعناية الواجب توفرها كي يتم العلاج
So, when we look at the pattern,
إذن، عندما نلقي نظرة على النمط في البيانات
one thing comes out very clearly:
هناك نقطة مهمة تظهر بوضوح
you see the blue bubbles
ترون الفقاعات الزرقاء
and people say HIV is very high in Africa.
يقول الناس أن إنتشار فيروس نقص المناعة مرتفع جداً في أفريقيا
I would say, HIV is very different in Africa.
ما أقوله أنا هو أن إنتشار الفيروس مختلف جداً في أفريقيا
You'll find the highest HIV rate in the world
ستجدون أعلى نسب الفيروس في العالم
in African countries,
متواجدة في دول إفريقية
and yet you'll find Senegal, down here --
مع ذلك، تجدون في السنيغال، في الأسفل هنا
the same rate as United States.
نفس النسبة الموجودة في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية
And you'll find Madagascar,
وتجدون في مدغشقر
and you'll find a lot of African countries
وفي الكثير من الدول الأفريقية
about as low as the rest of the world.
نسباً منخفضة مماثلة للنسب الموجودة في بقية العالم
It's this terrible simplification that there's one Africa
إنه ذلك التبسيط الفظيع لأفريقيا ككتلة واحدة
and things go on in one way in Africa.
وأن الأمور تسري بنفس الطريقة في أفريقيا
We have to stop that.
يجب علينا إيقاف ذلك
It's not respectful, and it's not very clever
طريقة التفكير تلك
to think that way.
لا تتسم بالاحترام ولا بالفطنة
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I had the fortune to live and work for a time in the United States.
كان لي الحظ أن أعيش وأعمل لبعض الوقت في الولايات المتحدة
I found out that Salt Lake City and San Francisco were different.
ووجدت أن مدينتي "سالت لايك سيتي" و"سان فرانسسكو" مختلفتان
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And so it is in Africa -- it's a lot of difference.
وهذا ينطبق على أفريقيا -- فالاختلاف كبير
So, why is it so high? Is it war?
إذن، ماذا يجعل النسب مرتفعة؟ أهي الحرب؟
No, it's not. Look here.
لا ليست السبب، انظروا هنا
War-torn Congo is down there -- two, three, four percent.
الكونغو، دولة مزقتها الحرب، النسبة فيها اثنان، ثلاثة، أربعة بالمائة
And this is peaceful Zambia, neighboring country -- 15 percent.
وجارتها زامبيا، التي يعمها السلام -- 15 بالمائة
And there's good studies of the refugees coming out of Congo --
وهناك دراسات كثيرة على اللاجئين الهاربين من الكونغو
they have two, three percent infected,
لديهم إثنان، أو ثلاثة بالمائة مصابين
and peaceful Zambia -- much higher.
وزامبيا المملوئة بالسلام -- أكثر بكثير
There are now studies clearly showing
هناك دراسات تشير بوضوح
that the wars are terrible, that rapes are terrible,
أن الحروب فظيعة، والاغتصابات مريعة
but this is not the driving force for the high levels in Africa.
ولكن هذا ليس السبب الرئيسي للنسب المرتفعة للمرض في أفريقيا
So, is it poverty?
إذن، أهو الفقر؟
Well if you look at the macro level,
حسناً، إذا نظرتم على المستوى الكلي
it seems more money, more HIV.
يظهر أن مع كثرة المال، يتكاثر فيروس نقص المناعة
But that's very simplistic,
ولكن هذا تبسيط كبير للأمر
so let's go down and look at Tanzania.
فلنذهب للأسفل وننظر إلى تنزانيا
I will split Tanzania in five income groups,
سأقسم تنزانيا إلى خمس فئات بناءً على مستوى الدخل
from the highest income to the lowest income,
من الفئة ذات الدخل الأعلى للأدنى
and here we go.
هيا بنا
The ones with the highest income, the better off -- I wouldn't say rich --
الفئات ذوات الدخل الأعلى، والتي وضعها أفضل، لن أوصفها بالغنى
they have higher HIV.
لديها مستوى أعلى من فيروس نقص المناعة
The difference goes from 11 percent down to four percent,
يتغير الفرق من 11 بالمائة إلى أربعة بالمائة
and it is even bigger among women.
ويكبر الفرق لدى النساء
There's a lot of things that we thought, that now, good research,
كثير من معتقداتنا تم نفيها من خلال أبحاث جيدة
done by African institutions and researchers
قام بها باحثون و مؤسسات إفريقية
together with the international researchers, show that that's not the case.
بالتعاون مع مؤسسات عالمية
So, this is the difference within Tanzania.
إذن ذلك كان الاختلاف في تنزانيا
And, I can't avoid showing Kenya.
ولا أستطيع تجنب عرض كينيا
Look here at Kenya.
انظروا إلى كينيا هنا
I've split Kenya in its provinces.
إذا قسمنا كينيا إلى محافظات
Here it goes.
كالآتي
See the difference within one African country --
لاحظوا الفروقات في دولة إفريقية واحدة
it goes from very low level to very high level,
إنها تبدأ من نسبة منخفضة جداُ إلى مرتفعة جداً
and most of the provinces in Kenya is quite modest.
ومعظم المحافظات في كينيا بسيطة جداً
So, what is it then?
إذن ما هو السبب؟
Why do we see this extremely high levels in some countries?
لماذا نرى مستويات مرتفعة من المرض في بعض الدول؟
Well, it is more common with multiple partners,
حسناً، يكثر شيوع المرض مع تعدد الشركاء الجنسيين
there is less condom use,
وقلة استخدام العازل التناسلي (الرفال)
and there is age-disparate sex --
ويتواجد الجنس مع التباين في العمر
that is, older men tend to have sex with younger women.
بمعنى أن الرجال الأكبر سناً يميلون لممارسة الجنس مع نساء أصغر سناً
We see higher rates in younger women than younger men
نرى نسباً أعلى بين فئة النساء اليافعات مقارنة بنفس الفئة من الرجال
in many of these highly affected countries.
في معظم الدول ذات النسب العالية من المرض
But where are they situated?
ولكن أين توجد هذه الدول؟
I will swap the bubbles to a map.
سأنشر الفقاعات على خريطة
Look, the highly infected are four percent of all population
الدول الأكثر إصابة تمثل أربعة بالمائة من كل سكان العالم
and they hold 50 percent of the HIV-infected.
ويحتوون على 50 بالمائة من المصابين بفيروس نقص المناعة
HIV exists all over the world.
هذا الفيروس موجود في كل أنحاء العالم
Look, you have bubbles all over the world here.
انظروا الفقاعات منتشرة في كل أنحاء العالم
Brazil has many HIV-infected.
البرازيل لديها الكثير من المصابين بالفيروس
Arab countries not so much, but Iran is quite high.
في الدول العربية لا يوجد الكثير، لكن في إيران عدد مرتفع
They have heroin addiction and also prostitution in Iran.
يوجد مدمنوا الهروين وتجارة الدعارة أيضاً في إيران
India has many because they are many.
الهند لديها الكثير لأنهم كثر
Southeast Asia, and so on.
وفي جنوب شرق آسيا ... إلخ
But, there is one part of Africa --
ولكن هناك جزء واحد في أفريقيا
and the difficult thing is, at the same time,
والشيء الأصعب هو، في الوقت ذاته
not to make a uniform statement about Africa,
من جهة، عدم التصريح برأي مماثل حول أفريقيا
not to come to simple ideas of why it is like this, on one hand.
وعدم الوصول إلى فكرة مبسطة لتفسير الأمر
On the other hand, try to say that this is not the case,
ومن جهة أخرى، الاعتراف بأن هذه حالة صعبة
because there is a scientific consensus about this pattern now.
لأن هناك إجماع علمي حول هذا النمط الآن
UNAIDS have done good data available, finally,
قامت الـ"يو إن إيدز" بتوفير بيانات جيدة أخيراً
about the spread of HIV.
حول إنتشار فيروس نقص المناعة
It could be concurrency.
ممكن أن يكون السبب تزامن العلاقات
It could be some virus types.
ممكن أن يكون السبب بعض أنواع الفيروس
It could be that there is other things
وقد توجد أشياء أخرى
which makes transmission occur in a higher frequency.
تزيد من نسبة انتقال الفيروس
After all, if you are completely healthy and you have heterosexual sex,
على كل حال، إذا كنت بصحة جيدة وتمارس الجنس الغيري
the risk of infection in one intercourse is one in 1,000.
فإن احتمال الإصابة في جلسة واحدة هي واحد في الألف
Don't jump to conclusions now on how to
لا تقفزوا للنتائج بعد
behave tonight and so on.
تأدبو هذه الليلة، وما إلى ذلك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But -- and if you are in an unfavorable situation,
ولكن -- إذا كنتم في وضع غير محبذ
more sexually transmitted diseases, it can be one in 100.
مزيد من الأمراض الجنسية المعدية، فقد تصل نسبة الإصابة إلى واحد في المائة
But what we think is that it could be concurrency.
لكننا نعتقد أن السبب قد يكون تزامن العلاقات
And what is concurrency?
وما هو التزامن؟
In Sweden, we have no concurrency.
في السويد، ليس لدينا تزامن
We have serial monogamy.
لدينا علاقات أحادية متتالية
Vodka, New Year's Eve -- new partner for the spring.
فودكا مع ليلة رأس السنة -- شريك جديد خلال الربيع
Vodka, Midsummer's Eve -- new partner for the fall.
فودكا مع ليلة منتصف الصيف -- شريك جديد للخريف
Vodka -- and it goes on like this, you know?
فودكا -- ويستمر الأمر هكذا... أتعرفون؟
And you collect a big number of exes.
ويتراكم عدد الشركاء السابقين
And we have a terrible chlamydia epidemic --
وينتشر داء المتدثرات (الكلاميديا) بشكل فظيع
terrible chlamydia epidemic which sticks around for many years.
ويبقى وباء داء المتدثرات منتشراً لسنيين
HIV has a peak three to six weeks after infection
يصل الفيروس ذروته بعد ثلاث إلى ستة أسابيع من الإصابة
and therefore, having more than one partner in the same month
ولذلك، فوجود أكثر من شريك واحد في نفس الشهر
is much more dangerous for HIV than others.
هو أخطر في حالة إنتشار فيروس نقص المناعة مقارنة بغيره
Probably, it's a combination of this.
على الأغلب، هو مزيج من ذلك
And what makes me so happy is that we are moving now
وما يسعدني هو أننا نتحرك الآن
towards fact when we look at this.
تجاه الحقيقة عندما ننظر إلى هذا
You can get this chart, free.
يمكنكم الحصول على هذا الرسم البياني مجاناً
We have uploaded UNAIDS data on the Gapminder site.
لقد قمنا بتحميل بيانات ال"يو إن إيدز" على:Gapminder.org
And we hope that when we act on global problems in the future
ونتمنى أنه عندما نتقدم لحل المشاكل العالمية في المستقبل
we will not only have the heart,
فلن نمتلك الفؤاد وحده
we will not only have the money,
ولا مجرد المال
but we will also use the brain.
ولكن سنستعمل العقل أيضاً
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)